<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Akhil Abroad: Understanding Uganda</title><description>Thoughts, stories and ideas.</description><link>http://localhost:2368/</link><generator>Ghost 0.11</generator><lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 19:09:22 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:2368/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title>Introduction</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Hello world! This blog contains the thoughts, reflections, and insights from my 2017 summer research experience in Jinja, Uganda as a Loewenstern Fellow. &lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/introduction/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">b149b63c-60b9-44fa-be53-d6a885142638</guid><dc:creator>Akhil Surapaneni</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 10:34:48 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Hello world! This blog contains the thoughts, reflections, and insights from my 2017 summer research experience in Jinja, Uganda as a Loewenstern Fellow. &lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Setting SMART Goals</title><description>&lt;p&gt;In life, they say you should go with the flow, &lt;strong&gt;but&lt;/strong&gt; sometimes that approach gets you stuck in the current. My summer in Uganda is probably going to be &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; different than how I am currently envisioning it and that is completely fine. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To avoid drifting through the summer and&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/welcome-to-ghost/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">b0656eac-3783-4f93-8b94-fe82d5d5ba14</guid><category>Getting Started</category><dc:creator>Akhil Surapaneni</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 08:33:18 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;In life, they say you should go with the flow, &lt;strong&gt;but&lt;/strong&gt; sometimes that approach gets you stuck in the current. My summer in Uganda is probably going to be &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; different than how I am currently envisioning it and that is completely fine. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To avoid drifting through the summer and regretting some aspects later, I figure it might be a good time to set up goals. In class, we talked about SMART goals:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Specific&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Measurable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Attainable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Realistic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Timely  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seems like a good method to visualize goals. So, after some soul searching (and some procrastination), I've come up with the following goals.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="goal1faithfullyexecutemyproject"&gt;Goal 1: Faithfully execute my project&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My project is to investigate the potential of using surface water to irrigate small crops in rural communities. So, my goal is that by the end of the summer, I should be able to tell if it is feasible or not.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="goal2learnluganda"&gt;Goal 2: Learn Luganda&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the key hallmarks to a mindful traveler is being respectful of the local culture. A great way to learn a culture is to start with learning the local language. The opportunities in the city open up, people start to open up, and the very semantics of language give insights into the local culture. By the end of the summer, I would like to have learned enough Luganda to take public transport and order food. This will give be my passport into Jinja.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="goal3avoidcommoditizingtheculture"&gt;Goal 3: Avoid commoditizing the culture&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Google Images search of Jinja, Uganda quickly shows why the city is called "The Adventure Capital Of Uganda". However, collated amongst the pictures of people white-water rafting and bungee jumping are also photographs of local people who are carrying out daily actions: images of their life. However, the issue is that the influx of tourists (who view the city as their vacation destination) feed the tourism business which can ultimately exploit the history and culture for profit. However, as a traveler, it is really hard to avoid perpetuating the system. My own goal is to buy goods from local vendors as much as possible. This at least puts money in their hands.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="goal4learnhowtocookatleasttwonativedishes"&gt;Goal 4: Learn how to cook at least two native dishes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This goal accomplishes two purposes. First, it helps me gain a better understanding of the local culture. Second, it might be a good way to better integrate with my host family. Hopefully I can get to know them better by spending some time making a meal with them. If I end up making something edible, then it might be a small token of giving back to my host family. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="goal5makeatleastonefriendinuganda"&gt;Goal 5: Make at least one friend in Uganda.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's always good to make new friends.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>