<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Akhil Abroad: Understanding Uganda</title><description>Thoughts, stories and ideas.</description><link>http://localhost:2368/</link><generator>Ghost 0.11</generator><lastBuildDate>Sun, 26 Feb 2017 20:38:46 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:2368/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title>Researcher's Role in International Development</title><description>&lt;p&gt;In class, we discussed whether we, student researchers abroad, have a role in international development. &lt;br&gt;
In my case, do I have an &lt;em&gt;obligation&lt;/em&gt; to  influence policy surrounding water access and conservation?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="nope"&gt;Nope&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got hired by Busoga Trust to evaluate technologies to improve water irrigation in rural communities. I've taken&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/researchers-role-in-international-development/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">86f09abd-7e85-499d-ae2d-7f5b6f84531e</guid><dc:creator>Akhil Surapaneni</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 26 Feb 2017 20:38:24 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;In class, we discussed whether we, student researchers abroad, have a role in international development. &lt;br&gt;
In my case, do I have an &lt;em&gt;obligation&lt;/em&gt; to  influence policy surrounding water access and conservation?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="nope"&gt;Nope&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got hired by Busoga Trust to evaluate technologies to improve water irrigation in rural communities. I've taken classes and done projects at Rice that have given me experience in doing this project. Furthermore, I will need to do a policy analysis to understand the obstacles to irrigation that currently exist. &lt;strong&gt;But&lt;/strong&gt;, I think that influencing the policy in the country is best left to the NGO. My attempts to do so will be seen as American meddling in Ugandan affairs. We talked a lot about how to be an ethical traveler. Attempting to meddle in politics will definitely make things worse. &lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Ethics in Photography Abroad</title><description>&lt;p&gt;During a lecture on the Ethics of Photography, that Dr. Paul Hester gave to the Loewenstern Fellows, I was reminded of the story of Kevin Carter. Carter was a South African photojournalist won the 1993 Pulitzer Prize for capturing a picture of a starving Sudanese child trying to reach the&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/ethics-in-photography-abroad/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">aa9a256a-5b46-4023-9887-139fdbd16ad6</guid><dc:creator>Akhil Surapaneni</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2017 00:14:57 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;During a lecture on the Ethics of Photography, that Dr. Paul Hester gave to the Loewenstern Fellows, I was reminded of the story of Kevin Carter. Carter was a South African photojournalist won the 1993 Pulitzer Prize for capturing a picture of a starving Sudanese child trying to reach the feeding center while a hungry vulture was waiting nearby. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;img src="http://www.unbelievable-facts.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/kevin-carter-vulture.jpg" alt="Starving child eyed by hungry vulture"&gt;
This photograph is very controversial. Some critics claim that Carter had a moral obligation to help the child. Others claimed that the picture is a lie of omission. While the toddler seems abandoned in the picture, in reality, a photojournalist who accompanied Carter claim that the parents briefly left the child to get food from a UN plane. This picture reminds me that a camera is essentially a lens for the photographer's eye. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking a picture &lt;em&gt;imposes one's biases&lt;/em&gt; onto the roll of film because those same biases &lt;strong&gt;color&lt;/strong&gt; one's vision of reality. Just like added bolded words and italics influences the meaning of the preceding sentence, the choice of lighting, composition, and color influence the reaction that a photograph elicits. Furthermore, the biases of my audience influences how they interpret the photograph. I think the key in taking ethical photographs is clearly identifying possible biases and trying not to inject my own into the picture. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is especially important that I take ethical photographs in Jinja because they are the first look into the city, district, and country for many of the viewers. It is hypocritical and wrong to exploit people's stories for the sake of a photograph, especially if I am only in the country to complete a project for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="sohowdoitakeethicalphotographs"&gt;So, how do I take ethical photographs?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I asked Dr. Hester this same question. First, he emphasized that it is important to ask the permission of everyone in the photograph. Information about them is released to the public, so it is critical that everyone has consented to that. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, I should take pictures in a way that maintains the dignity of everyone involved. Kevin Carter's picture diminishes the dignity of the parents because it omits them from the frame, implying that they abandoned this child. Pictures of starving African children flood the booklets and websites of NGO's. While poverty is a somber reality, these pictures don't showcase the remarkable resiliency of the communities depicted. They don't showcase the success stories. To accomplish this, it is very useful to ask how the subjects in the photograph want to be depicted. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also useful to build a relationship with the subjects, if people are being photograph. If the subject of the photograph is an object or location, it is important to learn more about the context and history. These will help bring my perspective closer to the truth, however you define it. In the same vein, photographs should be faithfully edited as to not distort the image from reality. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, I'm very excited to document my trip abroad. The lecture on the ethics of photography gave me some tools to do so in a responsible way. &lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>The Value of International Development</title><description>&lt;p&gt;When I first applied to go to Uganda, I was pretty excited to be able to help people. Now, I think I'll be happy if I didn't make anything worse. So what changed?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I just read a transcript of &lt;u&gt;To Hell with Good Intentions&lt;/u&gt;, a speech given by which&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/the-value-of-international-development/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">75c92466-ffa2-4232-9802-72a7d7cbfbf6</guid><dc:creator>Akhil Surapaneni</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2017 04:23:44 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;When I first applied to go to Uganda, I was pretty excited to be able to help people. Now, I think I'll be happy if I didn't make anything worse. So what changed?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I just read a transcript of &lt;u&gt;To Hell with Good Intentions&lt;/u&gt;, a speech given by which Ivan Illich to U.S volunteers in 1968. It takes a pretty pessimistic view of the role of international service. Illich claims that volunteers cannot possibly understand the people they are working with. Furthermore, they can't help but imposing their middle class American lifestyle onto the locals. He offers the following prediction of international volunteers.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;All you will do in a Mexican village is create disorder&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id="soisillichright"&gt;So, is Illich right?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The long answer is yes and no. We all know about those one week international &lt;em&gt;service&lt;/em&gt; trips: I was guilty of this too. In high school, I went to Tijuana, Mexico and built a house for a family over spring break. My high school does goes back to the same neighborhood every year to work on the same project for other families. But, I'm not sure if the one that we built still standing today or if future trips have done anything for that family. I do know that a lot of people on that trip got a new profile picture for a few months.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several implicit features of international service that I'm not comfortable with. &lt;br&gt;
First is the idea of Western superiority. If we are comfortable sending unskilled volunteers to address unmet needs in Third World countries, what value do we expect them to provide? If they have no training, then the implication is that we expect them to succeed by the virtue of being Westerners. &lt;br&gt;
Second, there is the mixing of tourism and volunteer work. It makes me cringe to think that people's poverty and life situation is the subject of another person's vacation plans.        &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I do believe that there is value in international service if it is done right. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="whatarethecharacteristicsofhelpfulservice"&gt;What are the characteristics of helpful service?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure the work is sustainable. During the Amigos training, they showed a video of Engineers Without Borders and their Save an African Child Spreadsheet idea. Engineering service projects are broken a few weeks after they are started because the locals aren't given the resources to maintain them. Then another engineering team comes in and does the same project over again, not knowing that they could've just fixed up the broken one.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Utilize an Asset Based Community Development Approach. This basically means utilizing local resources and local strength to promote development. With my project specifically, there are probably unique reasons why Water for Production technologies have not been implemented in Jinja even though they work perfectly well in the U.S. Each problem is different and therefore, each one needs a unique solution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning as much as possible about the dangers of international service so that others' mistakes are not repeated. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, to address the final question  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="isthereanyvalue"&gt;Is there any value?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, if done correctly. &lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Introduction</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Hello world! This blog contains the thoughts, reflections, and insights from my 2017 summer research experience in Jinja, Uganda as a Loewenstern Fellow. &lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/introduction/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">b149b63c-60b9-44fa-be53-d6a885142638</guid><dc:creator>Akhil Surapaneni</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 10:34:48 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Hello world! This blog contains the thoughts, reflections, and insights from my 2017 summer research experience in Jinja, Uganda as a Loewenstern Fellow. &lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Setting SMART Goals</title><description>&lt;p&gt;In life, they say you should go with the flow, &lt;strong&gt;but&lt;/strong&gt; sometimes that approach gets you stuck in the current. My summer in Uganda is probably going to be &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; different than how I am currently envisioning it and that is completely fine. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To avoid drifting through the summer and&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/welcome-to-ghost/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">b0656eac-3783-4f93-8b94-fe82d5d5ba14</guid><category>Getting Started</category><dc:creator>Akhil Surapaneni</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 08:33:18 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;In life, they say you should go with the flow, &lt;strong&gt;but&lt;/strong&gt; sometimes that approach gets you stuck in the current. My summer in Uganda is probably going to be &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; different than how I am currently envisioning it and that is completely fine. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To avoid drifting through the summer and regretting some aspects later, I figure it might be a good time to set up goals. In class, we talked about SMART goals:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Specific&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Measurable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Attainable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Realistic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Timely  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seems like a good method to visualize goals. So, after some soul searching (and some procrastination), I've come up with the following goals.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="goal1faithfullyexecutemyproject"&gt;Goal 1: Faithfully execute my project&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My project is to investigate the potential of using surface water to irrigate small crops in rural communities. So, my goal is that by the end of the summer, I should be able to tell if it is feasible or not.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="goal2learnluganda"&gt;Goal 2: Learn Luganda&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the key hallmarks to a mindful traveler is being respectful of the local culture. A great way to learn a culture is to start with learning the local language. The opportunities in the city open up, people start to open up, and the very semantics of language give insights into the local culture. By the end of the summer, I would like to have learned enough Luganda to take public transport and order food. This will give be my passport into Jinja.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="goal3avoidcommoditizingtheculture"&gt;Goal 3: Avoid commoditizing the culture&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Google Images search of Jinja, Uganda quickly shows why the city is called "The Adventure Capital Of Uganda". However, collated amongst the pictures of people white-water rafting and bungee jumping are also photographs of local people who are carrying out daily actions: images of their life. However, the issue is that the influx of tourists (who view the city as their vacation destination) feed the tourism business which can ultimately exploit the history and culture for profit. However, as a traveler, it is really hard to avoid perpetuating the system. My own goal is to buy goods from local vendors as much as possible. This at least puts money in their hands.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="goal4learnhowtocookatleasttwonativedishes"&gt;Goal 4: Learn how to cook at least two native dishes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This goal accomplishes two purposes. First, it helps me gain a better understanding of the local culture. Second, it might be a good way to better integrate with my host family. Hopefully I can get to know them better by spending some time making a meal with them. If I end up making something edible, then it might be a small token of giving back to my host family. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="goal5makeatleastonefriendinuganda"&gt;Goal 5: Make at least one friend in Uganda.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's always good to make new friends.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>